Andrew J. Emerick

CONTACT 614 W. 114th St. 313-399-1179

Information New York, NY 10025 emerick@astro.columbia.edu

RESEARCH Intend to focus of Interests magnetohydrodyn

Intend to focus on computational astrophysics. Previous astronomy work has included magnetohydrodynamical simulations of astrophysical plasmas, and the study of radio halos in galaxy clusters

EDUCATION Columbia University,

Ph.D., Astronomy, Expected: 2018/2019

University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN

B.S., Astrophysics, May 2013

- Summa Cum Laude, with Distinction
- Thesis Topic: Evolution of Weak Magnetic Fields in a Turbulent Plasma: A Galaxy Cluster Context
- Advisor: Thomas W. Jones, Ph.D.

B.S., Physics, May 2013

• Graduated with Distinction

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Undergraduate Research Assistant

Dec. 2011 - Aug. 2013

Minnesota Institute of Astrophysics, University of Minnesota - Minneapolis, MN Supervisor: Thomas W. Jones, Ph.D and David Porter, Ph.D

- Studying evolution of weak magnetic fields in turbulent plasmas using ideal MHD simulations at the Minnesota Supercomputing Institute.
- A portion of this research constituted my senior undergraduate thesis.

Undergraduate Research Assistant

Jan. 2012 - May 2012

Department of Physics, University of Minnesota - Minneapolis, MN Supervisor: Priscilla Cushman, Ph.D

- Worked with partner to characterize the gamma ray background in the Cryogenic Dark Matter Search detector testing facility.
- Used high purity germanium detector to lay groundwork for construction of appropriate lead shielding for testing apparatus.

Undergraduate Research Assistant

Oct. 2009 - Sep. 2011

Minnesota Institute for Astrophysics, University of Minnesota - Minneapolis, MN Supervisor: Lawrence Rudnick, Ph.D

- Worked on data processing and quality control for Green Bank Telescope observations done by graduate student
- Studied evolution of galaxy clusters using cluster radio halos as probes. Stacked faint, diffuse halos to independently confirm bi-modal distribution in radio halo properties.

Research Experience for Undergraduates

Summer 2011

Cyclotron Institute, Texas A&M University - College Station, TX

Supervisor: Ralf Rapp, Ph.D

- Utilized analytical reproduction of lattice QCD results to motive revisit of problem of bottomonium binding scenarios in the QGP.
- Used new understandings to update bottomonium production code to predict via observables, bottomonium yields at both RHIC and LHC.

Research Assistant

Summer 2010

Bonner Nuclear Laboratories, Rice University - Houston, TX Supervisor: Pablo Yepes, Ph.D

1 of 3

- Utilized Monte Carlo and first principles code to simulate proton radiation therapy.
- Improved first principles code with goal of more efficiently calculating relevant parameters in a fraction of Monte Carlo simulation run-times.

REFEREED JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

- A. Emerick, X. Zhao, R. Rapp, "Bottomonia in the Quark-Gluon Plasma and their Production at RHIC and LHC", Eur. Phys. J. A (2012) 47:72 doi: 10.1140/epja/i2012-12072-v
- S. Brown, A. Emerick, L. Rudnick, G. Brunetti, "Probing the Off-State of Cluster Radio Halos, 2011 ApJ 740 L28 doi: 10.1088/2041-82505/740/1/L28

Conference Publications

- 1. X. Zhao, **A. Emerick**, R. Rapp, "In-Medium Quarkonia at SPS, RHIC, and LHC" Nuclear Physics A, Vol. 904, p. 611-614c. Quark Matter 2012 Proceedings. Abstract
- 2. A. Emerick, T.W. Jones, D. Porter, "Simulation of Turbulence and Magnetic Field Evolution in Astrophysical Plasmas", *UMN Digital Conservatory: Undergraduate Research Presentations*. Poster
- 3. A. Emerick, X. Zhao, R. Rapp, "Bottomonium in the QGP: production at RHIC and LHC." Fall Meeting of the APS Division of Nuclear Physics: Bulletin of the American Physical Society, Volume 56, Number 12. Poster abstract
- 4. A. Emerick, S. Brown, L. Rudnick, "Stacking Detection of Diffuse Radio Halo Emission in Galaxy Clusters". In: AAS Meeting # 218, # 408.26; Bulletin of the American Astronomical Society, Vol. 43, 201. Poster abstract.
- 5. **A. Emerick**, S. Brown, L. Rudnick, "Examination of Radio Halos and Corresponding X-ray Emission in Galaxy Clusters", *UMN Digital Conservatory: Undergraduate Research Presentations*. Poster.

Unpublished Works

1. A. Emerick, "Evolution of Weak Magnetic Fields in a Turbulent Plasma: A Galaxy Cluster Context", Submitted to the University Honors Program at the University of Minnesota in partial fullfillment of the requirements for the degree of Bachelor of Science summa cum laude in Astrophysics. Full paper

AWARDS

Graduate Awards

 Dean's Fellowship Department of Astronomy, Columbia University Fall 2013, 5 yr

Travel Awards

• Conference Experience for Undergraduates APS DNP Fall Meeting

- Oct. 2011
- • Funding from University of Minnesota and APS Minority Scholarship May 2011 AAS 218^{th} Meeting - Summer Boston

Research Grants

Undergraduate Research Opportunities Program Grant
 University of Minnesota
 Undergraduate Research Opportunities Program Grant
 Fall 2010

University of Minnesota

Undergraduate Scholarships

J. Morris Blair Scholarship in Physics
 Dept. of Physics (UMN)
 Laverne and Ted Jones Undergraduate Scholarship
 Minnesota Institute for Astrophysics (UMN)
 Astronaut Scholarship Foundation Scholarship
 2012-2013

Minnesota Space Grant Consortium Scholarship
 Franklin Scholarship
 School of Physics and Astronomy (UMN)

• American Physical Society Minority Scholarship 2010-2012

2009-2013

• Gold National Scholarship University of Minnesota

Organizations

• American Physical Society (APS); Society of Physics Students (SPS), Sigma Pi Sigma: Physics Honors Society

Skills Computer Programming:

• C, C++, Fortran, LabVIEW, LaTex, Python, UNIX shell scripting, GNU make

References Thomas W. Jones

Professor of Astronomy

Minnesota Institute for Astrophysics

Phone: 612-624-1699

E-mail: twj@astro.umn.edu

University of Minnesota

Lawrence Rudnick

Distinguished Teaching Professor Phone: 612-624-3396 Minnesota Institute for Astrophysics E-mail: larry@astro.umn.edu

University of Minnesota